This BBC podcast is supported by ads outside the UK.
For years, I've sounded like a broken record.
I do not want kids.
I do not ever want to have kids.
I don't want to have a kid, don't want to have a kid, don't want to have a kid.
I'm in my 40s now. The door is almost closed.
And suddenly, I'm not so sure.
The story has always been no.
I'm just wondering to what degree it's just a story.
Definitely just a story.
From CBC's Personally, this is Creation Myth.
Available now wherever you get your podcasts.
And their victims were the Druids, an ancient religious order which was ruthlessly eliminated from Roman Britain.
The Druids were active in Britain, Ireland and Gaul and flourished for many centuries.
They were reasonably well chronicled by ancient authors including Julius Caesar and Posidonius.
Much later, thanks to a revival of interest in the 17th century, they inspired a wealth of literature and art.
But because the Druids were an oral culture and left no written records of their own, comparatively little is known about their beliefs and practices.
And the reinventions of the Druidical traditions by Romantic writers have resulted in much misconception and myth.
With me to discuss the ancient Druids are Justin Champion, Professor of the History of Early Modern Ideas at Royal Holloway, University of London.
Barry Cunliffe, Emeritus Professor of European Archaeology at the University of Oxford.
And Miranda Oldhouse-Green, Professor of Archaeology at Cardiff University.
Justin Champion, who were the Druids and where did they live?
The Druids really, I think, flourished between the late 4th century BC and the end of the 2nd century AD.
They're predominantly map onto the late Iron Age culture called Latin.
They're very eminent in England, in Britain, in Wales and in Brittany, in Gaul.
So they cover that period.
The problem we have is that the sources, the literary sources that expose their traditions are very, very fragmentary.
They're palimpsests, written over earlier traditions.
We know Druids existed in this culture because we can look at place names.
We can look at the spread of Celtic language.
But actually identifying the key areas is quite difficult.
One of the problems we have is that they were a determinedly oral culture.
Can you tell us why they were and what the consequence of that is?
Well, one of the problems is that they are a priesthood of some sort.
And they believe that they understand deep secret knowledge and that they pass it on to people of their own ilk.
That means that they don't leave artifacts and texts for us to study as modern historians and archaeologists.
And one of the problems is, is trying to coordinate the reportage of Druids in figures like Caesar and Pliny later with some of the archaeological temples and buildings that we know.
And certainly later on in the period, the 17th and 18th century, there's huge amounts of speculation about connecting that oral culture.
Of course, there are traditions in the early medieval periods that somehow draw from an oral tradition, particularly in Ireland.
And those, again, are exploited by 17th and 18th century figures.
But it's a very, very mysterious business.
Can we just go back for a moment or two, just not go back, go to this oral tradition idea?
Because many, many civilizations are remote from us because of their insistence on an oral tradition, which is fascinating.
You said they were priesthood.
They wanted to keep it among themselves.
But in a way, I think it I've read anyway, it's more extensive and deeper than that.
Can you just dwell on that for a moment or two?
I think one of the things that we we have difficulty with is, of course, Christianity became so dominant, even in the early centuries after Christ.
And that one of the projects that the Roman Empire alongside Christianity has was to actually obscure many, many aspects of that oral culture.
It has to be sort of destroyed.
It hasn't got to the point of why they insisted on it.
I've read it's because they thought that the writing was lazy, that they thought that writing was open to misinterpretations, which oral culture wasn't.
And are these any explanations?
Those are good, plausible explanations.
And certainly the Druids, because they read nature, they read sort of deeper philosophy, want to be able to communicate effectively with their local communities.
And, of course, writing is open to rhetoric and to exploitation.
There is one tradition, though, that says Druid thinking is captured in this mysterious language called Ogham, little marks on wooden sticks and on stones.
But, of course, we don't actually know very much about Ogham script itself.
And the invention of an oral tradition captured in that form is very much a 17th century tradition.
Barry Cunliffe, can you tell us then about the earliest chronicled references to the Druids?
Well, as Justin said, we've got lots of snippets of information about the Druids spread across a number of classical writers.
But from about the 1st century BC to about the 7th century AD, most of those classical writers are quoting secondhand, thirdhand, fourthhand from other classical writers.
So the game, really, is to try and sort out when the first and when the inputs of new information about the Druids sort of hit the literary world.
I think one could argue that the first input of real information comes around 300 BC with the journeys of a very remarkable man called Pythias who lived in Marseille.
He was a Greek. And he made a journey. We know about this journey.
He made a journey. I think he was trying to work out where the tin came from.
Tin was very important for the Greek economy. And it was coming from the northwest.
So he traveled through France, got into the Atlantic, probably took local boats, went to Brittany, crossed to Cornwall, up the Irish Sea, to the Northern Isles, down the east coast of Britain, down the Channel, and back to Brittany.
Back to Marseille, where he wrote a book called On the Ocean.
Now, that was the main source of information about the northwest of Europe, the Atlantic shores of Europe.
And that book, On the Ocean, we don't have.
But lots of other people started to use it as a source.
People like Timaeus, who was a Sicilian historian.
And people like Eratosthenes, a very interesting man around 200 BC, he was the librarian, chief librarian at Alexandria.
And people like that were using this early source.
And what were they finding about Druids in his account?
They were finding a lot about Britain.
And they were picking up little snippets of information about Druids.
And particularly, the theme that comes over is Druids as philosophers, as natural philosophers.
This is the early, let's call this the early Greek tradition, the Greek or Alexandrian tradition.
And that really does focus, not on all the ritual and blood and things like that.
It focuses on the intellectual quality of the Druid.
And the Greeks were very impressed.
They compared Druids rather to Pythagoras.
And Druids had these strange ideas that the soul was immortal, and so on.
Did Posidonius later, was it two centuries later, did he take up, did he build on Pythagoras' ideas?
He was an anthropologist, or did he do some original work of his own?
No, Posidonius was the next sort of input of new information.
Posidonius was a Stoic philosopher from Apamea in Syria.
He was Greek.
But he spent most of his time on the island of Rhodes, in the sort of university atmosphere of Rhodes.
But he was writing a history of the ancient world.
And like a good historian, he actually did his fieldwork.
And one of the bits of fieldwork he did was to go to southern France, Gaul,
when just a generation after the Romans had just taken over that southern strip of France,
ostensibly to work out how Hannibal got through the Alps and so on.
He was writing about that.
And he came across Celts and observed the habits of the Celts and the Druids and so on.
And he put a lot of new information into the pot.
What are the likely origins, the deep origins?
You've mentioned Pythagoras, the claims that it goes back to Moses, 13th century BC,
that it even goes back to Egypt, the Druid tradition.
Now, what are we to make of that?
What do you see as the origins?
Well, I think I can just take the evidence.
And what we've got to live with is a remark by Julius Caesar that the Druids originated in Britain.
And if you want to study the Druids, you've got to go to Britain to do so.
Now, we don't have to believe everything Caesar says.
Why did this business of Egypt, Moses and Pythagoras come in then?
Well, it was the later Greek writers who were looking back...
Was it Strabo and people like that?
No, people like Clement of Alexandria and some of the later Christians looking back on this
and saying that really the beliefs of the Druids were so much like Pythagoras
that either Pythagoras got them from the Druids or the other way around.
Belief being the transmigration of the cell, for instance.
That's right, that sort of thing.
But where the origin of the Druid belief came from, as Justin said,
it's concentrated in Britain, Ireland and France.
And that's where most of the place names, most of the evidence is.
And I think if you look, take Caesar's view that they might have originated in Britain.
Caesar, can I go across to Miranda for Caesar, Barry?
Do you mind?
Miranda, so we've got Caesar who gives us a very, quite a detailed account,
chronicle of the Druids.
Can you just tell listeners what he says about them?
Yes.
We take it he's a reasonably reliable historian.
He was on the case.
He was in Gaul for eight years.
He knew about this country as well.
Yes, he was in Gaul for about sort of eight or nine years in the 50s BC.
He was a Roman general and he wrote a war commentary called the Gallic Wars or De Bello Gallico.
And he, most of the books, there are seven books written by him in his lifetime and then one posthumous one.
But in book six, he digresses from his normal war diaries where he's talking about, you know,
conquering different tribes and polities in Gaul.
And he digresses to talk about customs and practices of Gauls and Germans and Britons to an extent.
And there's a quite a long piece in book six about the society in Gaul at the time he was writing.
And he says very tellingly that there were only two lots of people of any account, the Knights and the Druids.
And he's obviously far more interested in the Druids than anybody else.
He says they're in charge of all religious practices, that they are judges, they are teachers, they are natural scientists, they study the cosmos.
And they were immensely influential in all political and religious matters.
And Caesar is quite clearly quite impressed with them.
We learned later on, or not actually, but earlier on in the commentaries, that he had a very good friend called Diviciarchus,
who was the leader of a Burgundian tribe called the Aedui.
It's a Romanised name of a Celt.
Of a Celtic tribe, Diviciarchus, yes, indeed.
And he was a leader, but he was also in charge of religion.
And Cicero picks up Diviciarchus, who visited Rome in 60 BC, and Cicero meets him and talks about what an impressive person he is
and how good he is at divining the future, how good he is at augury, and he was a Druid.
So Caesar has this powerful ally, Diviciarchus, whom Cicero picks up on.
And the general impression you get from Caesar is that they are impressive intellectuals, they are worthy of Caesar's interest.
He also picks up on this business about oral tradition, Caesar, and he says quite clearly there are two reasons for lack of writing.
One is secrecy and the need to keep knowledge to the few.
And the second is to train memory.
And I think the whole idea about the Druids is that they are keepers of ancestral tradition.
They are, in a sense, the keepers of the culture of the communities in which they operated.
Is there any corroboration?
I mean, the interesting thing about Caesar's chronicle, apart from its interest, from what he says, is that it is detailed.
He claims an awful lot.
He makes a very grand claim for the Druids.
Is there any corroboration?
Is he alone?
What reasons do you have for believing him?
I think partly because he was surrounded by fellow Romans of similar status to himself.
He was writing his commentaries specifically to justify what were slightly dodgy actions in Gaul.
He didn't really have a mandate from the Senate for what he was doing in Gaul.
And I think part of the commentaries, part of the purpose of the commentaries was to legitimize what he was doing.
But he had people with him like Cicero's brother Quintus.
And I think had he sort of made it all up, I think people might have actually rumbled him and said something.
So although some of it may be sort of flannel and embroidery, I think he's one of our best sources.
Because the great thing about Caesar is he's writing at the time when the Druids were particularly prevalent.
What evidence did he put forward, if he put forward any evidence, that this had begun, the origin of the thing in north-west Europe was in Britain?
He actually says it is thought that Druidry began in Britain and was exported to Gaul.
And that's actually quite interesting because later on Pliny, who's another source of the Druids...
Pliny the Elder.
Pliny the Elder actually says exactly the opposite.
So who knows?
After Caesar, are there any classical authors who are as detailed and as convincing?
Not as detailed, but Pliny is quite...
He's quite interesting.
The later writers in the 1st century AD, there's a subtle change in how Druids are regarded by Romans.
So Caesar is fairly complementary about them.
People like Pliny, Tacitus and Lucan in the 1st century AD are fairly anti them.
And what you're getting now is the barbarian, the savage, human sacrifices talked up.
Is it propaganda or do you think it's a more realistic, more truthful analysis?
Well, a bit of both, I think.
Because the Romans didn't...
We're coming to that, but the Romans found the Druids an obstacle when they came to this country.
I think, yes, I think the Romans found the Druids a bit of a pain, partly because they were very highly nationalistic
and were clearly focuses of sedition and rebellion.
So when you are annexing a province, the last thing you want is Druids in people's ears going,
no, we don't want that.
And, of course, it's in the Druids' best interests for Rome not to succeed
because the whole of their power base would go.
Druids' power depends upon Gallic society and British society being hierarchical, highly stratified.
Once you bring Romans into the mix, the whole of society falls apart and is reinvented.
And there is no place for Druids in that.
So we're talking about the beginnings of a sort of propaganda.
And before we move on, when you say Davidiacus, Davidiacus met Cicero in Rome,
which language did they speak in?
Ah, Latin.
Right.
So the Druids knew Latin.
OK.
Well, enough.
If you can talk to Cicero, you're not doing badly.
No, indeed not.
OK.
Justin, Justin Champion, let's develop the idea of the Druids in society in Britain.
And we know quite a bit now.
So you just developed that.
How powerful were they?
The word power has been mentioned by Miranda.
I think, once again, we've got to be very cautious because we're drawing from these little fragments of sources
and sort of stitching them together.
You know, if we believe Caesar, the Druids are very highly organised.
You know, they have annual meetings.
They're arch-Druids.
They elect, they sort of confer and communicate across Gaul and Britain.
Within those societies, though, as Miranda said, that they are judges, they're teachers, they're motivators in some sense.
And I think that's one of the reasons why the Romans have difficulties with them.
The doctrine of the transmigration of the souls, I think it's Caesar says, makes men very brave.
Because if you know you may come back, then you're not going to be afraid to die in a war defending your own sort of community.
So I think we can think of the Druids as experts.
You know, they're not quite priests.
They're more than priests.
Certainly, as Pliny and the later sources expound and embroider on, they're involved with medical practice.
They're judges.
They're people who will negotiate between strife within communities.
So they're very powerful figures.
Caesar describes two sorts, knights and Druids.
Certainly, I think, after the Christian era, Druids are more and more marginalised and are starting to be thought of as sort of slightly odd magicians.
You know, they retreat, perhaps, out of communities.
So they're very powerful figures that we don't quite have a modern equivalent for, I think.
What do we know about the Druids' beliefs and rituals, then, Barry Cunner?
Well, strangely, very little.
We can pick up bits of it.
The Druid has...
If you're communicating as an ordinary person with the gods, you can only do so through the Druid.
So the Druid is an intermediary to start with.
So I want you to...
That's one point I was hesitating, stumbling off.
We're just in there.
But let's take it with you.
Was it a prime source of their power that they were, your word, the intermediaries between the gods and the...
They could do it.
They could take you to God.
They could tell you what God wanted to do and what God was going to do.
And that was the real keystone of their power.
Absolutely right.
As it is of most priesthoods, the priesthoods maintain their power because you, as an ordinary person, can't communicate with the gods without their presence.
And Caesar actually is quite specific about this.
He says that they can prevent you from communicating with the gods.
In other words, excommunicate you.
And no one will speak to you and you'll just fall apart and have to go away.
So they have immense power because they are the only way that you can contact the gods.
So you say we don't know much about their beliefs, but Christians began to claim that they, in some ways, prefigured Christianity.
Was that much later?
Yes, that comes later when people are trying to bring these two things together.
But we see them as the intermediaries.
There is one famous bit of ritual.
In fact, it's the only decent bit of ritual we've got, which Pliny talks about, which is the famous cutting of the mistletoe with a golden sickle.
And he explains this in quite a lot of detail, how you have to have the right time of the moon.
The moon mustn't be too strong.
It mustn't be too weak.
So you choose your time.
And that's one of the other aspects of the Druids' control, that they controlled our knowledge of time, when is an appropriate time to do things, when isn't an appropriate time to do things.
Very powerful, that is.
And then you had to dress in, the priest had to dress in white robes.
The mistletoe growing on the oak was particularly powerful.
And you cut it with a golden sickle.
It fell on a white cloth.
You sacrificed white oxen and so on.
So you get a sense of the complexity of belief and ritual there.
Why mistletoe?
I don't know what the particular power of mistletoe is, but the power of their belief in it was obviously very strong.
They said it was all curing.
But they also, and the same bit of Pliny, shows how very important their knowledge of plant law was and healing and the science of plants.
So we just get that little glimpse from Pliny.
Miranda, I'll just screen.
What was the, let's talk about the Druids now and the occupying Roman power.
In come the Romans.
There are the Druids.
There's a clash.
As you said earlier in your opening remarks, the Roman commentators change tone markedly once the Romans get into this country and decide they're going to make it part of the Roman Empire.
Can you talk about that, please?
Yes, I mean, there's an interesting episode, particularly in AD 60, which is rather a key year for Romano-British history, partly because of the rebellion of Boudicca, but also because it's the time when the Roman governor, Suetonius Paulinus, who was brought in by Nero particularly to, as a conquistador, as it were.
And Paulinus has decided that it's time to smash the Druids.
And the Druids have their Holy of Holies on the island of Anglesey.
Why is that?
Because Anglesey is on the edge of the known world.
Anglesey is an island.
Islands can be very sacred in antiquity.
And it was clearly, for some reason, considered there was a very holy grove there.
And that's where, when the Druids were sort of against the wall, as it were, they retreated.
Suetonius Paulinus took most of his legions and his auxiliaries all the way up to Anglesey.
How many people would that be?
Oh, we're talking about, I would say, about at least 20,000 people.
So he'd marched them up to Anglesey, 20,000 fully armed Roman soldiers.
Marched them up to Anglesey.
But the Druids weren't allowed to do military training.
So were they an unarmed bunch of people in Anglesey waiting to be slaughtered?
Well, it wasn't that they were not allowed.
They were exempt from military service.
But we also hear from Caesar, a rather pretty story, really, where if you wanted to be archdruid, you could actually fight your corner.
So they obviously weren't averse to the odd bit of sword play.
What do you mean, fight your corner?
Challenge the...
Challenge.
If you wanted to be archdruid, if you wanted to challenge the leadership, you might actually fight it out.
With a sword or whatever?
Yeah, which is a very pretty thought, in your long right robes.
But to go back to Anglesey, we know that our greatest source for this is Tacitus, who talks in quite some detail about the conquest of Anglesey.
And he talks about the Romans making flat-bottomed boats.
They get up the Medina Straits and land actually on Anglesey.
And they are met there by warriors and druids and sort of fanatical fury-like women, brandishing torches, and the druids are cursing.
And their weaponry is words.
We're going back again to the oral tradition.
Words, word power, satire, the ability of words and curses to turn something against the enemy.
Now, we have to remember that we always have this business that, you know, Gaul and Britain are very superstitious, rather barbaric and rather primitive and so on.
The Romans were unbelievably superstitious.
And the sight of these druids screaming imprecations at the soldiers trying to land would have been incredible psychological warfare.
So you have this picture of this sort of dense, armed mass of people and people armed with words and people armed with swords fighting to keep their groves safe.
And bottling up 20,000 Roman soldiers in the process.
But the Romans, from what I read, just slaughtered most of them.
They did, but they were interrupted.
It's not quite clear whether they actually managed the entire job.
Because while this is going on, Paulinus gets word that Boudicca is busy raising Roman towns to the ground.
Is there any connection, as I've read in the notes of somebody, one of you, that actually the druids wanted Boudicca to do that, to divert attention from Anglesey?
I think it was quite cleverly orchestrated.
I am quite sure that the druids were involved in this.
There is even a possibility, it's remote, that Boudicca herself might have been a druid.
Because we know that she was herself involved in divination, in sort of sacred groves in London.
And I think it was highly orchestrated, surely a coincidence, that Paulinus is up in the north-west and something happens in the south-east.
I didn't realise he'd taken so many troops.
That's a lot, isn't it?
It is a lot.
And one interesting thing, again, as Barry said, all this business about trying to get some archaeological evidence together with the written sources is so difficult.
But there's one theory I have, which I really like to posit here, and that is that on the way up to Anglesey, the Roman soldiers would have had to pass a place very close to Lindo Moss,
which is where Lindo Mann, a sacrificed young man, probably around that time, was found in 1984.
And I just wonder whether that was an aversion sacrifice to try and avert that disaster that was about to happen on Anglesey.
Justin Champion, why did the druids went into fairly steep decline, rather quickly?
Can you tell us why?
I mean, I'm pretty sure it's the result of Romanisation in both a military sense, but also in a legal sense,
because certainly at some point by the 60s AD, you can't be a Roman citizen and a druid,
so you're narrowing down the opportunities for learned men to go into the sort of business, if you like.
But after Mona, after the destruction at Anglesey...
Anglesey called Mona.
It's quite clear that Druidism is trying to be destroyed in all sorts of cultural ways,
and we don't really know that much into the early Anglo-Saxon period about what happens to them, I think.
But one can imagine, combined with Romanisation, the introduction of Christianity,
even if we believe some of the 17th century accounts, even this early, is a rival tradition.
I just wondered if we could perhaps add a little bit to that,
because there are later Roman writers who talk about Druids,
and that in itself is interesting because it means that the Druids remain in the Roman consciousness
right to the 4th century AD.
We have a poet called Osonius, a Bordeaux poet,
who wrote a very long treatise about his fellow rhetoricians at the University of Bordeaux,
and he talks about Druids, and by then he's talking of Druids being dynastic,
and the mantle of Druidism falling from father to son.
He actually mentions a number of people in this dynasty.
Now, whether or not these are the same kind of Druids that we would have found in Caesar,
I'm sure they weren't.
But the other interesting thing is a funny lot of documents called the Augustan Histories.
These date the sort of 3rd and 4th centuries AD,
and there are three or four stories about the accession to the purple of emperors like Aurelian,
Numerian and Diocletian,
and that is predicted by Gaulish Druidesses.
So what's interesting for me about that is that,
however much that may have been nonsense,
it means that Druids are still in the consciousness.
Barry Cunliffe,
although I've used the word exterminated,
as I've picked up properly,
that's not right, really.
They didn't disappear entirely,
and they're still continued in Ireland,
unconquered by the Romans.
Can you give us some idea how they drifted,
and this is ridiculous,
but for the next, well, say, 1,000 years,
after the 3rd, 4th century AD?
Yes, as you say,
they continued in Ireland for a while,
but were gradually turned into insignificance by the rise of Christianity.
But there were the Bards going on.
This Bardic tradition,
this oral tradition,
was an element of Druidism,
which continued into Irish society,
as indeed it did in Welsh society.
So if you're looking for any real thread of continuity,
the Bardic tradition in those two societies
is as good a thread as you can find,
but the religious overlay
has completely been wiped out by Christianity.
How reliable do you take the Bardic tradition?
Is it reinvented every 50 years,
every two or three generations?
Is there a real continuity?
There is a continuity.
Particularly in Wales,
it had almost died out.
At the Ice Stedfords,
you're getting about six or seven turning up.
When?
What day do we talk about?
We're talking about the 17th century.
The 19th century.
Oh, yes.
In the 18th century,
it begins to take off again
with the whole Celtic revival,
Celtomania.
But still,
we've missed out.
Have you got anything to get hold of
between about 400 AD and the 16th century?
Virtually nothing.
So what you're saying is
when it starts again in the 16th century,
they are making it up
as much as taking it for,
as much as inheriting it.
Yes.
From the 16th century onwards,
people are looking at the classical texts
and they are reinventing
a sort of romantic view of Druidism.
And you've only got these little threads
of things like the Ice Stedford,
like the storytellers,
which are a very pale reflection
of what went before.
Justin Champion,
John Aubrey in the 17th century
became interested in the Druids.
We know him from brief lives,
but he was an antiquarian
and some sort of archaeologist.
And the interest began,
which has never ceased really,
and he was one of the early,
let's call it modern,
persons to revive it.
Can you tell us about,
can you tell us what he did?
Aubrey in one sense
is a great under-explored scholar
and man of learning.
And he represents the sort of legacy
of Renaissance humanism.
As Barry's just said,
all of these classical texts,
whether it's Historia Augusta
or Pliny or Tacitus,
are rediscovered in the 16th century.
And nationalist scholars,
whether they're in France
or in England or in Ireland,
want to make a connection
with those sets of primary documents
and connect them
to their own particular communities.
So we'll get defences
of French Druidry,
English Druidry,
as texture things.
The step that Aubrey takes
is he goes out into the landscape,
to the ruins in the landscape.
He's perhaps the first field archaeologist.
And drawing from hints
from people like Inigo Jones,
who had studied Stonehenge
and was pretty much convinced
it was a Roman temple of some sort,
and reading sort of Danish scholarship
that say, no, no, Stonehenge
is a relic of a Danish conquest.
Aubrey goes out and measures,
draws, maps,
both Stonehenge and Avebury,
and then a whole series of other relics,
and makes the sort of intellectual leap
to connect those early sort of textual sources
with these real artefacts.
And I think from that moment on,
we can see the invention
of a whole series of Druidical practices.
And it's even more brilliant in one sense
that Aubrey is a great draftsman.
He commissions other representations.
And the drawings of Stonehenge
suddenly have little Druidical figures popping up
that he's lifted from another imaginative source.
And those representations persist.
I mean, they're reproduced
in many, many books today,
but they persist as ways of thinking imaginatively
about what Druids were.
Miranda, let's turn to Stonehenge
and William Stukeley
and the association that was there
for quite a while,
that Stonehenge was built by,
part of the Druids' tradition and religion.
Yes.
Can you tell this is about Stukeley?
Because Stukeley, as it were,
takes us on from Aubrey.
Stukeley does.
Stukeley's very interesting
because he's born in 1687.
He takes holy orders in 1729
and he becomes a clergyman
who then brings together his two great interests
in ancient religion and archaeology
and megaliths particularly.
And I think when we're thinking about Aubrey
and Stukeley and their fellows,
we have to remember that it's only comparatively recently
that we managed to get a long timeline
back into the remote past for Britain.
Before then, there was no means of, you know,
talking about a deep past,
a deep human past for Britain.
So Stukeley, like Aubrey,
saw Stonehenge as a pre-Roman temple.
The Druids were pre-Roman priests.
Therefore, Stonehenge must be associated with the Druids.
But Stukeley goes one step further.
He goes a bit strange after a while.
His sermons get more and more Druidic
and he finds an alleged inscription from Dijon
which talks about a Druid called Chindernax.
And Chindernax was a name that Stukeley adopted
and he began to sign his letters,
Your Sincerely Chindernax Druid.
So he didn't find any problem
with being clergymen and Church of England
at the same time.
No, no.
And I think that could have been partly,
if we can go back a little bit,
if you wouldn't mind,
to early Ireland and the interface
between paganism and Christianity.
We have wonderful documents
such as the 7th century lives of Bridget
and Patrick.
And Bridget is a particularly interesting one
because she grows up in a Druid's household
and he becomes Christianised
but remains a Druid.
And there doesn't seem to be a tension
between Christians and Druids.
I think your account of Stukeley is wonderful
and we need to sort of really emphasise
that he is doing Trinitarian archaeology.
Stukeley, in one sense,
subscribes to Usher's view
that the world is only about 6,000 years old.
So you've got to fit all of these things
from Adam to Moses to the Druids to now
into that chronology.
And he's reacting very, very much
against some of the deistical accounts
of the Druids as wicked pagan priests.
So Druidism is a form of patriarchal,
Abramic worship.
And it's not just Stukeley.
People like Isaac Newton,
supposed modern rationalists,
see Stonehenge as the remnants
of sort of ancient fire worship
that is only then contaminated
by corrupt Christianity.
Barrick, on Stonehenge,
it's been discredited that the Druids
could possibly have built Stonehenge.
It was built, hasn't it?
No.
Oh, I thought it was.
No, no.
Well, one of you told me that.
No, well, I think...
Who is a guilty contributor?
Yeah, there's some new ideas here
we've got to explore, I think.
The idea that Druids are to be related
with Latane culture, I think,
is an idea of the 50s and 60s
of the last century,
and most archaeologists have thrown that out.
If we try and find out...
If we look at the development
of religious structures
and behaviour in Britain
and look at what was happening
in the first century BC
when there were Druids
and then try and back-project
those behaviour patterns,
we can see that some elements
of the belief systems of the Druids,
cosmology, for example,
can be dated right back
to at least 3000 BC in Britain.
Some of the practices
of digging deep shafts
and putting offerings in them,
again, can go back
to the 3rd or 2nd millennium.
So I think there is a good case
to be made out
for the belief systems
of the Druids
from the 4th or 3rd centuries BC
are deeply rooted
in the belief systems
of the area
that go right back
into the Neolithic period.
But Stonehenge
is so emblematic.
Can you just...
You said...
Yes, they might...
Look, I'm...
There's a revolution
going on in my head.
I came here all prepared to put...
All right.
You say that they could have
had a hand in building it.
Or they could have built it.
Could be that.
No, no, not quite.
You're putting words
in my mouth here.
No, what I'm saying
is that the religious beliefs
which later are practiced
by the Druids
might be very deep-rooted
in Britain
and might be reflected
in buildings like Stonehenge.
Now, whether they were
calling themselves Druids
at that time,
who knows?
But we've got to look
for the roots
of these belief systems
and the roots go back in time.
Would it be fair to say, then,
that the Druids adopted Stonehenge
and for...
You're shaking your head again.
No.
Strangely enough,
there's no real evidence,
very little evidence...
Well, when did the...
We now think of Stonehenge
and the Druids together.
OK.
Well, let's get to...
Let me get to the hinge of it.
OK.
When did that happen?
Right.
People like Aubrey,
people like Stukley
came up with the idea
that Stonehenge
and Avebury
were the temples
of the Druids.
And that idea
has pervaded
scholarly and less scholarly
thought since then.
Now, what I'm saying...
Archaeologists have come in
and said,
absolute rubbish,
there are only Druids
from the 4th century BC.
Stonehenge is a lot earlier
than that,
so it can't be.
What I'm saying
with a number
of other archaeologists
is that the roots
go back deeper
and it's not impossible
that rituals
similar to those
of the Druidic rituals
were associated
with the building
and the early use
of Stonehenge.
I think, Barry,
that's why
the other figure
we could talk about,
John Toland,
is so interesting
because although
his critical history
of the Druids
and a specimen
of Celtic learning
is probably,
at the end of the day,
nothing more
than a very,
very elaborate joke
but a very
extraordinarily learned one,
he represents
some sort of early
pre-Egyptian,
pre-Pythagorean Druidism
taking place
not just in Ireland,
not just in Wales,
but certainly in Scotland
and he confects
this entire sort of
early Druid republic
where everything
is godly
and virtuous.
We've missed
our human sacrifice
and we haven't got
much time.
We've got to turn to it
because it's part
of the story.
They were accused of,
well,
there's been human
sacrifice in so many
religions and they
continue.
Can you,
and it was thought
by some early writers
and some early commentators,
was this black propaganda
that Miranda
you're going to tell us,
as being excessive,
that altars ran with blood,
that sort of thing.
What about human sacrifice
and the Druids?
What do we know?
I think it's fair to say
that human sacrifice
probably did take place.
There is some
archaeological evidence
for it,
for example,
in the bog bodies
places like Lindo Moss
that I've mentioned before
and quite a lot
of other evidence
but the archaeological
evidence suggests
that it was happening
but it was rare
and it would only happen
at times of great crisis
and I think what's happened
is that when Caesar
talks about it,
he talks about it
in a very matter-of-fact way.
He says it is,
the Druids find it
appropriate to sacrifice
human beings
for efficacious purposes.
They would try and use
prisoners of war
or criminals
but if there weren't
enough
then the innocents
would make up
the numbers.
He's very pragmatic
about this.
We have to remember
that human sacrifice
was only outlawed
in Rome in 97 BC,
not that long ago
before Caesar.
The other writers
like Pliny,
like Tacitus,
like Lucan,
they do sort of
talk it up a bit.
They do talk about
altars running with blood
but I think human sacrifice
did take place
but it was not
that out of the ordinary.
It was not
that big a deal.
Barry?
Barry Conner?
Yes,
there is evidence
in Iron Age archaeology
that bodies,
people were sacrificed
I think.
I excavated some pits
in a hill fort
called Dainbury
where there are bodies
thrown into the bottoms
of pits
with stones
heaped down on them.
Now that doesn't look
very much like
normal burial practice
so there are hints
like that
in the archaeological evidence
and indeed
the bog bodies
but I think Miranda
is absolutely right
that this was an extreme.
This was what you did
when things were going
really got bad
and you had to placate
the gods
rather like the Carthaginians
sacrificing their kids
when things went bad.
I think one of the
interesting things
is that the 18th
and 19th century
aren't really interested
in Druids as sacrifices.
They're interested
in Druids as recoverers
of some sort of
natural spirit
and the huge sort of effort
into reconstructing
Druidical temples
and saving land
Exactly
so they're communing
with nature
they're the sort of
early ecological
sort of warriors
in one sense.
Yes they are very much so
and these holy sites
become preserved sites
and the idea of preserving sites
owes a lot to that.
And even to the lengths
of very wealthy aristocrats
importing from Brittany
and elsewhere
sacred sites
and reconstructing them
in their own sort of land.
Well thank you very much
Barry Cunliffe
Justin Champion
Miranda Hodges Green
next year we'll be talking
about the ontological argument
first outlined
in the 7th century
by Anselm
the argument
is an attempt
to prove the existence
of God
through reason alone.
Thanks for listening.
If you've enjoyed
this BBC podcast
why not try others
such as The Forum
the discussion programme
about global ideas.
To find out more
visit bbcworldservice.com
slash forum
For years
I've sounded like
a broken record.
I do not want kids.
I do not ever want
I don't want to have a kid
don't want to have a kid
I'm in my 40s now
the door is almost closed
and suddenly
I'm not so sure
the story has
always been no
I'm just wondering
to what degree
it's just a story.
Definitely just a story.
From CBC's Personally
this is Creation Myth
available now
wherever you get
your podcasts.
Olympics
you
me